hey what's up guys my name is the
channel of them back to my C++ series
last time we talked about dynamic arrays
in C++ and specifically bit back to
class if you guys haven't seen that
video definitely check that out first
that's going to cover the basics of what
a dynamic array actually is and how to
use the vector class in C++ and this
video here is going to show you how you
might use that vector class in a more
optimal way a little bit about how it
works and just in general how we can
write our code so that it's just one
faster this is kind of exciting because
this is like our first kind of
optimization video and over the course
of this series we are going to be
talking a lot more about optimization
because they bus bus is specifically a
language which plays nicely with
optimization is a language that many
people pick due to the fact that they
might need some lower-level optimization
and one of the most important rules of
optimization is basically knowing your
environment and what I mean by knowing
your environment is how do things work
and what do I need to do exactly and
what should happen right and that's
that's such a complex topic in itself
that we are going to dive deeper into it
as the series goes on but for today
we're just gonna scratch the surface and
take a look at what we can do
specifically with the example of vector
so to optimize your vector usage you
really should know how vector works and
how you can maybe change it to work a
little bit better so basically the way
that the standard vector plus actually
works is you create a vector and then
you start pushing back elements and when
you add elements into that array to that
vector if the size of the vector if the
capacity of the vector is not large
enough to contain this new element that
you're trying to add basically what
needs to happen is the vector needs to
allocate new memory that is at least
large enough to hold this new element
you're trying to add as well as the
current contents of the vector and copy
everything across from that old location
in memory into the new location in
memory and then delete that old location
and that's what happens and so when we
try and push back an element if the
capacity runs out it performs that
resizing that reallocation and that
specifically is one cause of kind of
slow code it's the fact that if we
continually need to reallocate that's a
slow operation we need to reallocate
when we need to copy all of our existing
elements that's something we want to
avoid and in fact that's going to
largely be our optimization strategy
today copying
how can we avoid copying our objects if
we're dealing with vectors and
specifically dealing with object based
vectors so we're not storing a better of
pointers were actually storing a vector
of objects now I've said that knowing
your environment is one of the most
important things with optimization and
right now we're trying to optimize for
copying so we need to know when copies
actually happen and why they happen
let's take a look at some card and
figure that out so from the last video I
had this vertex class I just added a
constructor to it but we basically have
this kind of default part it's pretty
simple we have our two vertices that
we're pushing back nothing too fancy now
let's take a look at what actually
happens behind the scenes and identify
how many if any copies are actually
happening with this current code so a
good way to do that is to add a copy
constructor to vertex and maybe either
put a breakpoint in there or just print
something to the console to see when
that copy constructor actually gets
called so what I'm going to do is just
write a copy constructor if you're not
sure what a copy constructor ears or how
copying actually works in C++ then
definitely check out the video that's
linked in the top right corner but I'm
just going to write a very very simple
copy constructor for this vertex class
now for the purposes of this video don't
really need to fill it out properly but
I don't so anyway what I'm going to do
is print copied over here to our console
so that we can take a look at that and
let's run this code okay so we get three
copies interesting I'm actually going to
add another element here and this time
since I can I'm just gonna use the
actual constructor just so that this
code looks a bit easier to read so I'll
make this seven a nine and in fact I'm
going to squish over my existing ones as
well to use this kind of new constructor
that I've made this is just the original
default constructor it does exactly the
same thing as the code before but I
think it might just be a little bit
easier to read because you know exactly
what's happening okay so if I run this
code how many copies do expect six we
have six copies now you might be asking
yourself why why is that happening why
is C++ copying my vertex six times in
total what's going on to debug this a
little bit further I'm gonna place a
breakpoint on this line and run this
code again so we have zero copies at the
moment of course because we've met we
haven't even pushed anything back let's
let's hit f10 so now we've pushed one
element back one vertex and we have a
copy right why is that happening the
reason that's happening is
because when we construct our vertex
we're actually constructing it in the
current stack frame of the main function
so we're constructing it on the stack in
main and then what needs to happen is we
need to put it into that into that
vector right so we need to somehow get
it from that main class from the main
function rather not class function from
the main function into the actual vector
into the memory the vector has allocated
and of course the way that we do that is
we copy it from the main function into
the vector class that's our first kind
of mistake that's the first thing we can
optimize what if we could just construct
that vertex in place in the actual
memory that the vector has actually
allocated for us
that's optimization strategy number one
which we'll implement in a second but
let's keep going
now if I get F 10 over here we get two
more copies so if not went out three
copies right so we already know what's
happened we already know where one of
the copies has gone us because we were
constructing this vertex object on
inside the main function then pushing it
into the vertices vector which causes a
copy but then why are we getting an
additional copy what's going on well if
we hover our mouse over this and we take
a look at the actual vertices vector we
can see the capacity is two what that
means is that this this vector
physically has enough memory to store
two vertices or two vertex
objects so what happens of course is
when we try and push another one on like
this third one and I hit f10 it needs to
resize the capacity to three or two
anything higher than two basically so
that we can actually have enough memory
to push in a third vertex so that's
another potential optimization strategy
our vector is being resized twice here
it just it's it's at one by default it
then moves to two when we have the
second element and then moves to three
when we add the third element if we know
our environment if we know that we are
planning to push in three vertex objects
why don't we just tell the vector hey
make it off memory for three so that you
don't have to resize yourself twice just
make enough memory from three from the
beginning because I plan to actually
push in three elements
that's optimization strategy number two
which we'll implement in a minute as
well so that is the idea of where these
six copies are coming from
so let's do the quick and easy
optimization strategy I guess let's just
tell the vector hey I want you to please
have the capacity of three and the way
that we can tell the vector I want to
have the capacity of three is by simply
after we created setting vertices dot
Reserve three and you can see that that
takes in a capacity now this is
different to resize or if we were to
pass them three in the constructor if we
actually try and pass them three in the
constructor this code won't even compile
and you can see if I just move this up
there that we're getting as vertex no
appropriate default constructor
available because what this will
actually do is not just allocate enough
memory to stall three vertices or three
vertex objects it's actually going to
construct three vertex objects we don't
want to construct any objects yet we
just want to have enough memory to hold
them that's what Reserve does Reserve
makes sure that we actually have enough
memory so the first step is we create
this vertices vector and then we reserve
three and then we push back our elements
let's take a look at how many copies we
now get with this with the addition of
this one line of code look at that three
copies instead of six that's half as
many copies and of course this kind of
goes up exponentially if we add ten
that's gonna be a lot more copy so we've
saved it
we've saved a great deal of copies
already so this is great but we can do
better
we're still getting a copy because this
vertex is actually being constructed
over here inside the main function and
then copied into the actual vector I
would like to just construct it in the
actual vector and the way that we can do
that is by using in-place back instead
of push back and so in this case instead
of actually passing a vertex object that
we've constructed we instead just passed
the parameter list for the constructor
which basically tells the vector hey
constructive vertex objects with the
following parameters in place in our
actual vector memory so I'll do that for
all of these and we'll replace a push
back with em place back
let's hit f5 look at that clean clean as
a whistle that is a nice looking console
out but not a single copy in this code
anymore do you see how we've just
optimized this really easily by just
knowing how it works and being aware of
the fact that our vertex object was
actually getting copied like six times
it's not even hard to write code but
this
specifically is gonna run a lot a lot
faster than the code that we originally
had and it didn't even take long to
optimize it's just about knowing what's
actually going on knowing our
environment and knowing how we can
actually optimize using the tools that
we have available anyway I hope you guys
enjoyed this video that's like a first
kind of introduction to optimization I
love talking about this stuff so we are
going to be talking a lot more about
this kind of stuff in this a fuzz ball
series if you enjoyed this episode
please hit the like button if you want
to see more videos and you want to help
support the series then head on over to
patreon Macomb 4/2 Cherno you'll get
some cool rewards for supporting the
series such as being able to see videos
early contribute to the planning of the
videos and a few more perks which you
can check out on that site I will see
you guys next time
good bye
[Music]